Your company launches a search for an open position.
بدأت شركتك البحث لملئ وظيفة شاغرة.
The applications start rolling in,
بدأت التقديمات بالانهمار،
and the qualified candidates are identified.
وتم تحديد المرشحين المؤهلين.
Now the choosing begins.
الآن بدأت مرحلة الإختيار.
Person A: Ivy League, 4.0, flawless resume,
الشخص أ: ايفي ليغ، 4.0، سيرة ذاتية مثالية،
great recommendations.
توصيات رائعة.
All the right stuff.
كل الأشياء المطلوبة.
Person B: state school, fair amount of job hopping,
الشخص ب: خريج مدرسة حكومية، قدر لا بأس به من التنقل بين الوظائف،
and odd jobs like cashier and singing waitress.
أشغال متعددة مثل أمين صندوق ونادلة.
But remember -- both are qualified.
ولكن تذكروا، كلاهما مؤهل.
So I ask you:
لذا سؤالي هو:
who are you going to pick?
من ستختارون؟
My colleagues and I created very official terms
زملائي في العمل وأنا ابتدعنا مصطلحات رسمية للغاية
to describe two distinct categories of candidates.
لوصف فئتين مختلفتين من المرشحين.
We call A "the Silver Spoon,"
نسمي الشخص أ "الملعقة الفضية"
the one who clearly had advantages and was destined for success.
وهو الذي حظي بامتيازات واضحة وكان مقدرًا له النجاح.
And we call B "the Scrapper,"
ونسمي الشخص ب "المشتبك"
the one who had to fight against tremendous odds
وهو الذي توجب عليه النضال لتجاوز صعوبات عظيمة
to get to the same point.
حتى يصل إلى نفس النقطة.
You just heard a human resources director refer to people
لقد سمعتم لتوكم مدير موارد بشرية يشير إلى الناس
as Silver Spoons and Scrappers --
بالملاعق الفضية والمتحدين
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
which is not exactly politically correct and sounds a bit judgmental.
الشيئ الذي لا يعتبر صحيح سياسيًا ويبدو حكميًا بعض الشيئ.
But before my human resources certification gets revoked --
ولكن أمام موظفي العاملين في الموارد البشرية فإن الشهادة تفقد دورها
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
let me explain.
دعوني أوضح.
A resume tells a story.
السيرة الذاتية تحكي قصة.
And over the years, I've learned something about people
وعلى مدى السنين، فقد تعلمت شيئا عن الناس
whose experiences read like a patchwork quilt,
الذين تبدو خبراتهم مثل الثوب المرقع،
that makes me stop and fully consider them
الشيئ الذي يجعلني أتوقف وآخذهم بعين الإعتبار
before tossing their resumes away.
قبل أن أرمي بسيرهم الذاتية بعيدًا.
A series of odd jobs may indicate
إن سلسلة من الأشغال المتفرقة قد تشير إلى
inconsistency, lack of focus, unpredictability.
عدم الثبات، وفقدان التركيز، وعدم القدرة على التنبؤ.
Or it may signal a committed struggle against obstacles.
أو قد تكون إشارة إلى النضال المستمر ضد العقبات.
At the very least, the Scrapper deserves an interview.
على أقل تقدير، المشتبك يستحق إجراء مقابلة معه.
To be clear,
كي أكون واضحة،
I don't hold anything against the Silver Spoon;
أنا لا أكن شيئا سيئا ضد الملعقة الفضية:
getting into and graduating from an elite university
حيث أن الإنضمام إلى والتخرج من جامعة مرموقة
takes a lot of hard work and sacrifice.
يتطلب الكثير من العمل الشاق والتضحية.
But if your whole life has been engineered toward success,
ولكن في حال ما تم هندسة كل حياتك نحو النجاح،
how will you handle the tough times?
فكيف لك أن تتعامل مع الأوقات الصعبة؟
One person I hired felt that because he attended an elite university,
أحد الأشخاص الذي عينتهم تعرض لذلك الإختبار بسبب أنه التحق بجامعة مرموقة،
there were certain assignments that were beneath him,
كانت هناك مهام معينة اقل من مستواه
like temporarily doing manual labor to better understand an operation.
مثل القيام مؤقتًا بعمل يدوي بغرض فهم أفضل لعملية ما.
Eventually, he quit.
ولكنه استقال في آخر المطاف.
But on the flip side,
ولكن على الجانب الآخر،
what happens when your whole life is destined for failure
ماذا يحدث عندما تكون كل حياتك مقدر لها الفشل
and you actually succeed?
ولكنك رغم ذلك تنجح؟
I want to urge you to interview the Scrapper.
أنا أحثكم على إجراء مقابلة مع المشتبك.
I know a lot about this because I am a Scrapper.
أنا اعلم الكثير عن هذا الأمر لأنني أنتمي لنفس الفئة.
Before I was born,
قبل أن أولد،
my father was diagnosed with paranoid schizophrenia,
تم تشخيص حالة والدي بانفصام الشخصية،
and he couldn't hold a job in spite of his brilliance.
ولم يستطع الحصول على عمل برغم ذكائه.
Our lives were one part "Cuckoo's Nest,"
كان حياتنا في جزء منها أشبه بفيلم "عش الوقواق"،
one part "Awakenings"
وجزء أشبه بفيلم "المستيقظون"
and one part "A Beautiful Mind."
وجزء آخر مثل فيلم "عقل رائع"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I'm the fourth of five children raised by a single mother
ترتيبي هو الرابعة من بين خمسة أطفال ربتهم أم عازبة
in a rough neighborhood in Brooklyn, New York.
في حي تصعب الحياة فيه في بروكلين، نيويورك.
We never owned a home, a car, a washing machine,
لم نمتلك منزلا على الإطلاق، ولا سيارة ولا غسالة،
and for most of my childhood, we didn't even have a telephone.
وطيلة أغلب فترات طفولتي، لم نمتلك حتى جهاز هاتف.
So I was highly motivated
لذلك كنت أتمتع بدافعية قوية
to understand the relationship between business success and Scrappers,
لفهم العلاقة بين النجاح في العمل والمشتبكين،
because my life could easily have turned out very differently.
ببساطة لأن حياتي تحولت بشكل مختلف للغاية.
As I met successful business people
عندما قابلت أناسا ناجحين في مجال الأعمال
and read profiles of high-powered leaders,
وقرأت ملفات قادة على مستوى رفيع،
I noticed some commonality.
لاحظت بعض القواسم المشتركة:
Many of them had experienced early hardships,
العديد منهم تعرضوا لمصاعب في فترات مبكرة،
anywhere from poverty, abandonment,
على مختلف الأصعدة من الفقر والهجران
death of a parent while young,
وموت أحد الوالدين خلال سن مبكرة،
to learning disabilities, alcoholism and violence.
حتى صعوبات التعلم وادمان الكحول والعنف.
The conventional thinking has been that trauma leads to distress,
لطالما كان التفكير التقليدي أن الصدمة تقود إلى المحنة،
and there's been a lot of focus on the resulting dysfunction.
ولطالما كان هناك الكثير من التركيز على الخلل الناتج.
But during studies of dysfunction, data revealed an unexpected insight:
ولكن خلال فترة اجراء الدراسات على الخلل، كشفت الدراسات عن حكمة غير متوقعة:
that even the worst circumstances can result in growth and transformation.
أنه حتى أسوء الظروف يمكن أن ينتج عنها النمو والتحول.
A remarkable and counterintuitive phenomenon has been discovered,
حيث تم اكتشاف ظاهرة استثنائية وحدسية،
which scientists call Post Traumatic Growth.
والتي يسميها العلماء نمو ما بعد الصدمة.
In one study designed to measure the effects of adversity
في احدى الدراسات المصممة لقياس تأثير الصعاب
on children at risk,
على الأطفال المعرضين للخطر،
among a subset of 698 children
ضمن شريحة من 698 طفل
who experienced the most severe and extreme conditions,
الذي تعرضوا لأشد الظروف وأقساها،
fully one-third grew up to lead healthy, successful and productive lives.
تمكن ثلثهم من إدارة حياة سليمة وناجحة ومنتجة.
In spite of everything and against tremendous odds, they succeeded.
حيث أنهم نجحوا على الرغم من كل شيئ ورغم عظيم الصعاب.
One-third.
الثلث.
Take this resume.
ألقوا نظرة على هذه السيرة الذاتية.
This guy's parents give him up for adoption.
منح والدا هذا الفتى ابنهم للتبني.
He never finishes college.
لم ينهي دراسته الجامعية.
He job-hops quite a bit,
تنقل بين عدد من الأعمال لفترة.
goes on a sojourn to India for a year,
أقام مؤقتا في الهند لمدة سنة،
and to top it off, he has dyslexia.
وعلى رأس القائمة فهو يعاني من عسر القراءة.
Would you hire this guy?
هل كنتم لتوظفوا هذا الفتى؟
His name is Steve Jobs.
اسمه ستيف جوبز.
In a study of the world's most highly successful entrepreneurs,
في دراسة حول أكثر رواد الأعمال نجاحًا في العالم،
it turns out a disproportionate number have dyslexia.
يتضح أن عدد متفاوت منهم يعاني من عسر القراءة.
In the US,
في الولايات المتحدة،
35 percent of the entrepreneurs studied had dyslexia.
35 في المئة من رواد الأعمال الذين شملتهم الدراسة يعانون من عسر القراءة.
What's remarkable -- among those entrepreneurs
الشيئ الاستثنائي، حول رواد الأعمال هؤلاء
who experience post traumatic growth,
الذين جربوا نمو ما بعد الصدمة،
they now view their learning disability
هم الآن يرون صعوباتهم التعلمية
as a desirable difficulty which provided them an advantage
كصعوبة مرغوب فيها والتي أمدتهم بميزة
because they became better listeners and paid greater attention to detail.
لأنهم أصبحوا مستمعين جيدين وأعطوا اهتماما أكبر للتفاصيل.
They don't think they are who they are in spite of adversity,
هم لا يفكرون بأنهم وصلوا إلى ما عليه اليوم برغم الصعوبات.
they know they are who they are because of adversity.
بل يعرفون أنهم ما عليه اليوم كنتيجة لهذه الصعوبات.
They embrace their trauma and hardships
إنهم يتقبلون ما تعرضوا له من صدمات وصعوبات
as key elements of who they've become,
كعناصر أساسية في ما أصبحوا عليه اليوم،
and know that without those experiences,
ويعلمون أنه لولا هذه التجارب،
they might not have developed the muscle and grit required
لربما ما استطاعوا تنمية القدرة والعزم اللازم
to become successful.
لكي يصبحوا ناجحين.
One of my colleagues had his life completely upended
أحد زملائي قلبت حياته تمامًا
as a result of the Chinese Cultural Revolution in 1966.
كنتيجة للثورة الثقافية الصينية عام 1966.
At age 13, his parents were relocated to the countryside,
ارتحل والداه إلى الريف حينما كان بعمر 13 سنة،
the schools were closed
كانت المدارس مغلقة
and he was left alone in Beijing to fend for himself until 16,
وقد تُرِكَ وحيدا في بكين العاصمة ليعتني بنفسه حتى بلغ 16 سنة،
when he got a job in a clothing factory.
حيث تحصَّل على عمل في مصنع للملابس.
But instead of accepting his fate,
ولكن بدل أن يرضخ لواقعه،
he made a resolution that he would continue his formal education.
اتخذ قرارًا بأن يكمل تعليمه النظامي.
Eleven years later, when the political landscape changed,
بعدها بإحدى عشر سنة، عندما تغير المشهد السياسي،
he heard about a highly selective university admissions test.
سمع عن اختبار قبول لجامعة مرموقة للغاية.
He had three months to learn the entire curriculum
كان لديه 3 أشهر لكي يتعلم كامل منهج
of middle and high school.
المرحلة المتوسطة والثانوية.
So, every day he came home from the factory,
لذلك، كان يعود كل يوم من المصنع،
took a nap, studied until 4am, went back to work
يأخذ قيلولة، يراجع دروسه حتى الرابعة صباحًا، ثم يعود إلى العمل
and repeated this cycle every day for three months.
وكرر هذه الدورة كل يوم لمدة ثلاثة أشهر.
He did it, he succeeded.
ولقد نجح فعلا.
His commitment to his education was unwavering, and he never lost hope.
كان التزامه بتحصيل التعليم لا يتزعزع، ولم يفقد الأمل مطلقًا.
Today, he holds a master's degree,
اليوم، هو حاصل على درجة الماجستير،
and his daughters each have degrees from Cornell and Harvard.
وكلتا بنتيه حاصلتان على شهادات من جامعتي كورنيل وهارفارد.
Scrappers are propelled by the belief
المشتبكون يدفعهم الإيمان
that the only person you have full control over is yourself.
بأن الشخص الوحيد الذي تملك كامل السيطرة عليه هو نفسك.
When things don't turn out well,
عندما لا تسير الأمور بشكل طيب،
Scrappers ask, "What can I do differently to create a better result?"
يتساءل المشتبكون، "ماذا بوسعي أن أفعل بشكل مختلف حنى أحصل على نتيجة أفضل؟"
Scrappers have a sense of purpose
المشتبكون يشعرون بأن لديهم هدف
that prevents them from giving up on themselves,
الشيئ الذي يحميهم من الإستسلام،
kind of like if you've survived poverty, a crazy father and several muggings,
مثل لو أنك نجوت من الفقر، ومن أب مجنون و العديد من حالات السطو المسلح،
you figure, "Business challenges? --
فتقول، "تحديات الأعمال؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Really?
حقًا؟
Piece of cake. I got this."
منتهى السهولة. لقد فهمتها."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And that reminds me -- humor.
وذلك يذكرني بالدعابة.
Scrappers know that humor gets you through the tough times,
المشتبكون يدركون أن الدعابة تساعدك على تجاوز الأوقات الصعبة،
and laughter helps you change your perspective.
والضحك يساعدك على تغيير وجهة نظرك.
And finally, there are relationships.
وأخيرًا، هناك العلاقات.
People who overcome adversity don't do it alone.
الأشخاص الذين يتجاوزون الصعاب لا يفعلون ذلك لوحدهم.
Somewhere along the way,
في مرحلة ما،
they find people who bring out the best in them
يجدون أشخاصًا يخرجون أفضل ما فيهم
and who are invested in their success.
ويستثمرون في نجاحهم.
Having someone you can count on no matter what
أن تجد شخصًا تعول عليه بغض النظر عن أي شيئ آخر
is essential to overcoming adversity.
هو شيئ أساسي لتجاوز الصعاب.
I was lucky.
لقد كنت محظوظة.
In my first job after college,
في أول وظيفة لي بعد التخرج،
I didn't have a car, so I carpooled across two bridges
لم أكن أمتلك سيارة، لذا كنت أعبر جسرين
with a woman who was the president's assistant.
برفقة إمرأة كانت مساعدة الرئيس.
She watched me work
شاهدتني وأنا أعمل
and encouraged me to focus on my future
وشجعتني على التركيز على مستقبلي
and not dwell on my past.
وأن لا أنغمس في ماضي.
Along the way I've met many people
خلال مسيرتي قابلت العديد من الناس
who've provided me brutally honest feedback,
الذين أمدوني بملاحظات صادقة دونما مجاملة،
advice and mentorship.
نصح وارشاد.
These people don't mind
هؤلاء الناس لا يمانعون
that I once worked as a singing waitress to help pay for college.
أني ذات مرة عملت كنادلة لكي أدفع رسوم جامعتي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I'll leave you with one final, valuable insight.
أخيرًا سأترككم مع حكمة قيمة.
Companies that are committed to diversity and inclusive practices
الشركات الملتزمة بالتنوع والممارسات الشاملة
tend to support Scrappers
تميل إلى دعم المشتبكين
and outperform their peers.
حيث يتفوقون على أقرانهم.
According to DiversityInc,
طبقًا ل دايفرستي
a study of their top 50 companies for diversity
في دراسة حول أفضل 50 شركة من حيث التنوع
outperformed the S&amp;P 500 by 25 percent.
تفوقت في دليل S&amp;P 500 (دليل سوق الأسهم الأميركي) بنسبة 25 في المئة.
So back to my original question.
رجوعًا إلى سؤالي الأساسي.
Who are you going to bet on:
على من ستراهنون:
Silver Spoon or Scrapper?
الملعقة الفضية أم المشتبك؟
I say choose the underestimated contender,
أقول اختاروا المرشح الأقل أهمية،
whose secret weapons are passion and purpose.
من أسلحته الخفية الشغف والهدف.
Hire the Scrapper.
عينوا المشتبك.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)